[Music]
Welcome to this business central launch
edition of 2025 release wave 2. This
session is about PowerBI updates for
projects and inventory.
The video have two parts uh for
inventory and one for projects. for the
updated inventory PowerBI app. The main
news is that you can now forecast your
inventory needs based on past
performance. And uh this helps you get
more proactive in ordering new items
from your vendors in time so that you
actually have um the stock on demand um
so you don't run out of it when
customers want to uh are likely to
order. So that means fewer missed sales,
happier customers, uh hopefully and uh
and less stress for your team. It's all
about staying ahead of demand and stay
instead of being reactive. And if you
use the project module, uh do check the
updated PowerBI app as well. This is uh
now open source and um and ready for any
customizations that you might want to
do. uh you can tailor it to your
business needs, track progress more
effectively and surface insights uh so
that you deliver your projects on time
and on budget and uh one thing we added
to the actual reports there is a little
bit more focus on profitability of your
projects. So u so let's uh let's dive in
and see those in action. So, let me show
you um how you can forecast your
inventory with a new report inventory
forecasting.
By default, it's just showing with no
filters a forecast based on the periods
in time you would like kind of to go
back. Forecasting in PowerBI is AI. It's
classic AI. It's machine learning. It's
a statistic statistical model. So
nothing to do with generative AI but
still very powerful. Um and uh basically
it's it just tries to forecast with uh
yeah with the data in that data window
what's going to happen in a period of
time in the future and all of that is
something you can decide. We chose to
also have shown upper and lower bounds
in the forecast. You can mod modify and
change everything here to your liking.
We also added a regression like a a
trend line here. You can see the dotted
line. Maybe it's hard on the video, but
a trend line for the actual data as
well.
Now, it might be not really useful to
have an forecasting on everything, every
quantity in your inventory. you probably
want to dive more into some like area
and and and see either by item or a
location like where you are. So of
course uh you can do that. Uh we added
these three visuals down here with
location item or uh item ledger entry
type. Uh so it's easy to navigate
directly from these or to filter. So if
I for instance want to to forecast
what's what will be uh needed from my
yellow warehouse where my inventory is
available there the visuals will change
to that. Um if I want to forecast to any
of my items I can just choose them. Now
the data here is is not representative.
You will have much better data for that.
And of course, if you want to zoom into
other areas of u of this forecasting,
you can you can see I chose to forecast
on the last uh two months, April and
May. But uh but you can change the look
behind the window here as well as any
other things you might want to uh look
at like item categories, uh items, lot
number, serial number, and so on. So
that's kind of how you use the
forecasting report. U you probably
filter to something and you kind of see
what would be the uh based on the past
the statistical future of of this time
series.
Now um since this is a statistical model
um it's actually quite advanced. It it
the model knows knows about seasonality.
it knows about um like a lot of things
that you can control. So the way you can
control the like the window look ahead
window upper bounds and seasonality is
um simply to go and modify this visual
here for the forecast and if I choose
visualizations for that there's a a menu
normally for PowerBI you only have two
menus but here for the forecast you have
one more that uh this is the one where
you can control the look and feel or the
behavior here and you probably need to
do that to adjust the forecasting to the
type of business you are. For instance,
uh here in the forecast menu, I can
choose uh the forecast length. I can
also choose seasonality. Let me just
make this a little bit bigger here. So
the seasonality here can be uh like uh
one or two or three seasons depending on
if you are if you sell Christmas
decorations you probably have
seasonality of one. If you have other
seasonal uh changes in your business you
can choose that here. So so that's
important to know that. So play around
with the forecasting parameters so they
kind of match the way you do business
and uh and hopefully you'll be able to
um predict the future based on the past
um with uh with this new forecasting
report.
All right, let's let's shift gears and
look at the PowerBI app for projects. So
as I mentioned in the introduction the
profitability and open sourcing are the
two main areas for this um this release.
So um and actually one more thing also
that we uh we added the different types
of things you can sell in projects to
the model as well. I'll show you in a
few seconds. So I chose uh just one
report here project invoice sales by
type to illustrate these two points
profitability and the new types
profitability. Uh you can see like a new
um visual here billable to invoice
percentage. Of course I can choose or
filter to different customers different
projects and then uh these numbers will
change. uh but also notice here on on
the left that we now have invoiced uh
price or amounts by type. So both
resources, items and GL accounts, things
you can sell through projects is now
showing up both in the model and in the
report. And then finally um the project
invoiced sales by type table down here
has a lot more profitability measures so
that you can also depending on the type
of things you sell uh you can you can
see how profitable it is. If you want to
analyze not your sales by type of things
you sell but by customer might be a more
um well in some cases more um realistic
scenario. You can do that in the new or
updated project invoice sales by
customer. So here you have your billable
to invoice. If I choose to filter to a
school of fine arts, you can see my
billable to invoice percentage visual is
then changing. And I can also uh if I
choose again one customer, I can kind of
look into the profitability of this
particular customer as seen from the
project side. And the one thing you
probably want to do right after this uh
video is to go learn more. And there are
two links you need to know. If you're
interested in doing analytics on your
inventory, the aka.ms/bcinventory
analytics will take you to a landing
page where you can learn everything
about scenarios, about personas and
different uh PowerBI and normal reports
that can help you analyze uh your
inventory area.
If you are more interested in the
project site, we have a similar um thing
here aka.ms/bc
project analytics and that takes you to
the same type of landing page. Now for
project analytics again show showing you
scenarios, personas, PowerBI reports,
anything you need in case you need to
analyze the project business.
That's it. Two more things you need to
see actually three. LinkedIn. If you're
not following our product group on
LinkedIn, please do. There's an aka link
for that. This is where we communicate
all the tiny bits of pieces of
information when it's ready for the
public. And that goes outside our normal
release cadence. So, go follow us there.
And since you are seeing this on
YouTube, you probably know that we have
a YouTube channel. If not, go and and
follow us there. Our YouTube channel
from the engineering team is also where
we put out like small bits of new
information, tips and tricks, co-pilot
and AI deep dives and so on. So
aka.ms/bc
YouTube is where you get to our YouTube
channel. And if it's not enough with
those two, we actually have a landing
page aka.ms/bcall.
This is the landing page for all the aka
links in the world for partners. So if
you don't know that resource, just
bookmark that. If you have any
questions, comments, discussions as a
business central partner, our Yammer
site is where that happens. So BC
Yammer, go uh go and make sure that you
enroll and get into the conversations
with the rest of us. And finally, office
hours both for customers and partners
aka.ms/bc
office hours. This is where we have
monthly calls on different topics.
everyone is uh can can join that and
kind of learn about the direction of
business central. That's it. Thank you
so much for watching and have a great
Business Central launch edition. Thank
you.